[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings you relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio is brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine online at computer org
slash software for software engineering
radio this is Stefan silikov today I'm
joined by Kyle Kingsbury better known by
his Twitter handle a fear to talk about
database consistency kyle has become
quite famous in the community because of
his tendency to break databases that is
use rigorous testing to show how they
deal with various error scenarios I've
been a longtime follower of Kyle's posts
and talks and I'm sure you'll be as
fascinated as I am by his insights into
the theory and practice of data bases
handling failure or unfortunately more
often failing to do so to varying
degrees Kyle why don't you start off by
introducing yourself and tell us a
little bit about yourself oh well my
name is Kyle I'm the back-end engineer
by trade and I work right now at a
company called stripe where I'm doing
database safety analysis trying to
understand whether or not distributed
systems
cassia's databases queues that sort of
thing whether or not they live up to the
guarantees that we expect from them okay
so for those of our listeners who
haven't really you know been exposed to
those kinds of problems can you talk a
little bit about what issues might arise
when when people use technologies like
that sure thing we see consistency
problems all the time for example you
might go to Twitter and read some direct
messages and then go from the website to
your phone and you've noticed the same
direct messages are shown as unread
that's a that's a synchronization
problem a consistency problem where
different computers different clients
have different ideas about the state of
the system and this goes much deeper you
can get into errors with bank accounts
for example there is a famous Bitcoin
exchange that
lost a lot of money because it's not
correctly debit and credit accounts in a
transaction Facebook for example has all
sorts of interesting out of order issues
with display these are these are
problems that arise sometimes because
there's simply no good way to do them at
scale and sometimes just because we
didn't understand what the necessary
safety credits were so is this something
that that only companies that run really
really big data centers are exposed to
do I have to be running something like
Facebook or Twitter to run into those
kinds of problems I don't think so but
it's tricky to give a good data about it
because most people don't instrument
their consistency they don't measure
whether or not the system is actually
safe so one of the things I'm trying to
answer is how likely is it the you might
see real world impact during certain
common failure modes so one of the
things that I often run into is that
people who use traditional relational
databases
you know the Oracles and db2 Zo's and my
sequels and Postgres whatever those
kinds of things believe that they don't
have to worry over about those things
are they right yeah you know it depends
like there are certainly consistency
issues in relational databases as well
there was a paper published recently
actually on a Postgres error where it's
serializable isolation level failed to
be serializable in a sort of surprising
way and so I think you'll find these
safety issues affect people who through
the level of bugs and just because
understanding the weaker ANSI SQL
isolation levels is a little bit tricky
the spec is not entirely clear about
what shouldn't shouldn't happen can you
talk a little bit for those isolation
levels not necessarily all of them but
give us an idea about what is specified
there that's your thing so as I
understand it as relational databases
are was coming into their own different
database companies realized that it was
impossible to provide complete nice
global orders for events in the system
you want all your transactions to look
like they take place sequentially one
after the other but actually doing that
is relatively expensive and so maybe
there are shortcuts maybe you could
avoid eating out a complete lock and a
lot to transact rizzo times to save data
to complete at the same time
when you do that there are different
treat outs you can make regarding how
long your bar locks for whether you look
for reads or writes if you do
multi-version concurrency control you
can get different sort of what we call
anomalies there their behavior patterns
orders in which transactions can execute
that look maybe a little bit dodgy in
some cases they're okay but in some
cases they're not for example we get a
problem called phantoms where you might
write a new record into a data set and
at the same time you make a query
against a table and that query should
have seen the new record but does not
because it's predicates didn't yet match
for whatever reason and so maybe maybe
access to the same row in the table is
synchronized correctly but that row
might not appear in a query that should
have seen it it's a sort of subtle
reason about so what happened was the
different database manufacturers were
certainly starting to standardize and
nobody wants to be left out so we have
this this standard ansi SQL but that
codifies different levels of safety and
those levels sort of correspond to
whatever trade-offs the davis's might
have made historically it's that
everybody could say it is slaughtered in
somewhere so practice you'll get a wide
variety of interpretations of those
anomalies and then different levels of
actual conformance suit to the spec one
thing that I find interesting is that
you can actually specify some of those
or configure them right you can make a
decision of what kind of isolated little
you want so um so this idea is nothing
new it's been there for a long long time
that that people can make create I have
to make trade-offs regarding consistency
levels right exactly yes you can choose
to jack up the series the isolation
levels serializable for every
transaction but this is this is somewhat
slow so a lot of people will start off
at recommit we're even back after a
uncommitted depending on what their
application needs that's the ideal case
but some people you know will just turn
it down to read uncommitted or leave it
the defaults because it's faster without
understanding implications and without
fully reasoning through the transactions
I think it's sort of an open research
problem right now we're not sure which
transactions which which patterns of
access and database
which I solution levels disease so how
is this related to the famous cap
theorem and can you maybe explain that
to us a bit so see well so there's a
there's two things there's actually a
cap theorem which is a formal proof by
gilbert and lynch and that tells us that
of consistency which they mean linearize
ability availability which they mean
total availability that is every request
to Anam failed note and on crash note
must succeed and of partition tolerance
that's the p in cap you can only have
two out of three now that actually
derives from a sort of conjecture or
informal claim but error that of
consistency availability of virtually
tolerance there's some trade off you can
really only get two out of three so when
people talk about cap in a modern
context i think they're typically
referring to the proof which is very
strict definitions about what
availability consistency mean but that
doesn't mean that by relaxing
consistency you necessarily get
availability their terms with other
proofs that exclude different classes of
of operations different position classes
from being fully available as well so
cap is a very particular example of the
sort of larger class of problems of
consistency a consistency model is a a
set of allowing histories allowed
behaviors that a database could go
through so if you were to take all the
different operations you do like reading
a value and writing it into some other
table or incrementing a number or
setting three fields at once on a given
record those are all sort of
transactions if you think all the
transactions in a system the in practice
the different transactions are applied
somewhat concurrently you know maybe
somebody is writing data and somebody's
reading data at the same time what you
want is for the operation is to take
place in some kind of order so maybe
part of a transaction takes place first
and another transaction sneaks in and
does a little bit of work and another
transaction comes in there's a little
bit of work the first transaction comes
in finishes there's lots of different
ways those events can be ordered and the
consistency model is the class of
allowed orderings of those events so cap
tells
is about a very particular consistency
model just like ansi SQL tells us about
certain allowed models like read
uncommitted read committed they prohibit
certain classes of orders they prohibit
you for example from reading the result
of another transactions right until your
transaction is committed or you might
get snapshot isolation where all of your
operation is supposed to take place on
some atomic snapshot of the world that
occurs at some logical time just before
you commit those consistency classes can
only be achieved in certain availability
models and there's different theorems
that tell us which classes are
achievable and which image of the
ability settings cap tells us that one
of the strongest classes of consistency
the more than which allows the least
number of reorderings well not the least
but you know for a very small number
it's still infinite it's complicated cap
tells us about linear eyes ability which
is this very strict ordering and it says
that linearizable systems cannot be made
to be fully available if you build a
linearizable system and it experiences a
network partition a communication
failure between nodes it's possible for
transactions to stall forever or for
transactions to be incomplete you either
have to deadlock or give up on certain
operations I think everybody can imagine
what consistency means sort of you
mentioned linear eyes ability and you
know the system goes from one consistent
state to another and you have this this
feeling that there's no there's no you
don't get you don't get a dirty read of
some kind you don't get half committed
things and you don't miss anything that
has been has been written or has been
committed I think everybody can imagine
what availability is about but I always
feel that people struggle with the city
of partition tolerance what is it what
why do I use a term like that is it what
does it actually mean oh that's interest
on house yeah all it means is that the
system should be resilient or should
continue to function in the event that
messages are not delivered okay okay and
we see this happen in production network
all the time
Microsoft ran a really interesting paper
in sitcom a couple years ago where they
measured their database packet loss over
several years and they have a lot of
machines on a lot of routers now
gave pretty good quantitative evidence
about the frequency and severity
partitions it turns out to be far more
common you would expect even with good
change control even with good hardware I
think okay so a partition can can occur
for for any number of reasons it doesn't
matter whether it's actually the network
being down or you know some other
problem along the along the weights for
some reason the message doesn't arrive
at the node it was supposed to arrive at
is that does that what it's about yeah
exactly
so it could be a delay because delays
and drops are sort of from one another
on a timescale if I'm allowed to
arbitrarily delay a message I can always
outweigh you as a software system
because at some point you're gonna say
well all right I give up it's not going
to happen so you can get garbage
collection pauses for example when a run
time stops stops execution of the
program to clean up some memory no
messages will flow in or out so that
introduces a delay and that can look
like a narrow partition the operating
system you know if a disk scheduler goes
south a lot of times that will stall IO
operations and so here's stop waiting
for the kernel to do some IO your
program might not be running anymore and
C again has a sort of delay network
partitions can happen from the actual
network you know if you have a cable
that gets killed by a backhoe or
unplugged you'll get into logical
software errors where a race condition
occurs and some messages never get sent
there's all sorts of different ways this
can happen okay so if I if as you said a
I can pick any two from those from those
three properties can you walk us through
the three options I'll do they all
actually exist and and what what kind of
you know what's the what's the result if
I have a CA a CP or an AP system so what
two out of three really means well the
papers very explicit it says it here for
help addition you must use either AP or
CP and experimentally it looks like
networks do experience partitions on a
rail of the treatment timescale given
the versions are going to happen I think
we should make a PCP trade offs okay so
there is no CAE because there is no
system that doesn't that doesn't run
into partitions any time in same time if
you have a synchronous network and
you're very diligent about maintaining
it you're okay however any system which
is CP can also be totally available if
the network doesn't partition so you
might as well shoot for AP or CP and
simply in the common case when the
network is working do everything
correctly ok so you can help both as
long as the network is running and then
you'd agreed to want the other it's sort
of like asking if something bad happens
your network which are you going to
preserve okay so so let's talk about
those two AP and CP what it was the what
kinds of trade off am i making if I
choose one of those two databases offer
you availability first and foremost and
that means total availability that you
can make a request to any node you can
make it right you can make a read you
could make a updated a complicated query
it parents that whatever you want to do
against any node is fine this makes them
really good candidates for highly
available systems in a single data
center but it also makes them good
candidates for distributed systems that
are geographically replicated because
you can write independently in any given
data center and with low latency
immediately return results so that's a
wonderful property right everybody wants
that for people who who could who
consider that does an AP system give up
consistency completely or what is what
does it actually mean to have an AP
system so the cap theorem is total
inability and there's a whole bunch
different proofs to tell you what the
sort of maximal consistence in all those
are you can get there's actually
infinitely many but the common ones are
going to be
writes follow reads so you guarantee
that if you do a read of an upper a read
of a given value that you're right is
logically successor to that you can get
monotonic reads where if you've read two
things in a row on the same session
they're gonna happen sequentially in
these sort of lock core of the system
monotonic writes where I write will
follow it right you can get recommitted
monatomic atomic view and also a PCI
which I do not remember what the acronym
stands for but all those things are
totally available so you can have these
these guarantees what your system will
do there's no consistence it's just that
they don't exclude all
operation I see so having an AP system
just means that I don't have 100 percent
consistency doesn't mean that i you know
i don't i don't give a consistency
completely i run in to say i make some i
make some trade-offs regarding
consistency to achieve this 100 percent
availability it's not like it's a
fractional consistency it's that it is
100% consistent with respect to that
consistency model so your system is
completely safe if it obeys certain
rules for example if you use C or D T's
conversion replicated data types um it's
okay to do updates anywhere you like and
they'll eventually convert from some
value if if that's your data model you
know a system like react or Cassandra
where it's taping and it doesn't offer
you any sort of guarantees about when
you're going to read data that is that
is safe but you can't do all all things
with it if you want to do a counter for
example in react you have to deal with
the fact that you might write a value
and somebody else might not see it for
quite a while until that data is
replicated over so you have to be ok
with with allowing more histories wider
windows of concurrency in the system
okay youyou already mentioned two
examples of AP systems do you have a
bunch a bunch more that you could just
briefly mention nothing I'll explain
what I think we'll get to that just tell
us what our typical AP systems yeah so
dynamic loans which comes out of the
paper called Dynamo from Amazon there's
also Baltimore's and a few others the
sort of lesser I mean though a lot of
people don't think about them this way
but I think if you have like a cluster
memcache machines or a cluster or buy
these machines that are sort of
independent and you're on your charting
layer on top of them
in a lot of cases that is sort of
analogous to an AP system now it depends
you know CP is also sort of rare because
in order to be truly CP you need to be a
linearizable and relatively few days so
let's talk a bit about CP then there
will be another trade off I give up some
availability I don't have an unavailable
system I have a system that that makes a
higher priority of consistency than
other available
right so I restrict this property of
having as you mentioned any node be able
to accept a right or eat so what is a
typical kind of system that I get if I
want if I should for CP as opposed to ap
so yeah exactly you can still be highly
available but you cannot be totally
available so in a CP system the trade
off you'll typically see is maturity
quorums where you must have a majority
of notes reachable and connected to
nerds make progress if you're on the
sort of minority island or if you're on
single notes isolated you've given up
the ability to do some oral operations
you might be able to get a reduced set
of operations like maybe I couldn't read
data but it's not guaranteed to be
recent anymore so the really common ones
here are gonna be zookeeper at CD even
when disco has a passive plantation side
of it I think foundation DBE is claiming
to be relatively strong although I don't
know if they promise serialize full
strong serializability and there's
there's a broader class so linearize
ability can't make certain guarantees
about the wall clock time if I write a
value to linearizable database and then
it comes back and says okay you're right
is complete I am guaranteed that anybody
else that makes a request after that in
wall clock time will see that right but
there are other strong consistency
models which are also not totally
available so sequential consistency
which guarantees you have a total order
of all events and that every process
sees the same ordering that is not
totally available serializability and
strong serializability which simply
enforce there must be a total order
we're not sure what it is
those are both perimeters well you can't
even hamper putable reader snapshot
isolation or cursor stability which are
the kind of strong ones on the SQL side
of things those ones cannot be total
available either so if you were to build
a cluster of you know my sequel and it's
like what is a proponent to something
like this if you like an oracle cluster
or whatever there are theoretical upper
bounds on how available that cluster can
be nor but to meet the guarantees is
curse disability repite will read so on
very nice so after all this theory maybe
let's able to go to some to some
practical practical things right so one
of the things that I found really
fascinating is that you did not only
ride a bunch of smart blog posts or what
we did but you did not only write them
you know based on academic theory you
actually tested systems and in the
system that you develop for that all the
Toula to develop is called Jepsen can
you talk a bit about what that is and
how you ended up building it yes none of
the things that I've said are
particularly novel right this is all I
think relatively well understood
research in the academic field dating
back to really the eighties however I
think if you're a practitioner right now
somebody who's going out and building a
back-end for a website or something it's
really not common for somebody in that
position to have the time or the
interest or the the Trinity to go and
read academic papers it's not an easy
thing to absorb even for me like it
takes me a full week to read a paper
what do I read where do I start there's
no good books and because consistency is
not something that's going to bite me
right now if I'm under a time crunch
which I think pretty much all engineers
are I'm just going to prioritize
building more features and getting stuff
out the door and if people start to
complain I'll go look at safety and
consistency so we're in a world where
engineers are not cognizant of the
literature and don't believe that the
literature describes failure modes that
could actually happen to their system
and it's unclear because we're not
measuring our systems whether or not
that's a real problem right like okay I
you know read a Sentinel seems to be
really unsafe and these sort of academic
wankers say it's unsafe but is it really
like it seems too fine to me I've added
numbers and I've done reads in this in
DB alright so I wanted to build an
experimental harness to actually measure
whether or not these theorems had sort
of measurable real-world consequences so
how did you go about that I mean you
would have to set up all of those
systems and Andrew drive some abstract
thing what was the actual process that
took you there
so Tom santero and Mark Phillips asked
me to give it a talk at recon
distributed systems conference in New
York in 2013 and I scrambled to figure
out what to do I I knew I want to talk
about consistency wasn't sure how to
build how do I really do this
verification thing so the software that
I wrote was very simple it just said
what's gonna let's add a bunch of
numbers to a set and then we'll read the
set and if all the numbers we inserted
are there it's good practice on baby so
this this doesn't require you know you
can you can reorder stuff in between but
it's something we can implement on most
databases and get some understanding of
the CD properties ok so how did you how
did you build that what database did you
pick and how did you how did you end up
building this this kind of thing
originally I wanted to do react because
there was the mailing was discussion
about the last write ones behavior so I
did react there was something from
Matthew res that I thought was old dodgy
and Sentinel so I was like all right
let's take a look at Redis to order to
do MongoDB because that's sort of a very
common popular database that a lot of
people are running out but has
historically it's public perception and
has not always been so positive as far
as safety goes and then Postgres which
has this reputation of being you know
completely safe and an ironclad and in
effect you know they're doing very good
engineering work but there are some
subtleties that you might not think
about so I threw those four databases
and harnesses for each one that hooked
them up to this little set machine right
so it's gonna add add add at numbers and
then do final read and we'll check to
see how many were dropped and how many
were present in the final set that we
thought might have failed it has all
these do computes and then I I started
out by running a proxy actually to you
everybody's database would talk to my my
proxy software and it would route the
connections for you and drop them that
turned out not to work very well
and so what I had to back off to was
running each one in a separate VM and
Nitra might be slow so I've had them in
Etsy instances and that kind of worked
that's why I wanted up in a sort of
horrible mishmash of shell scripts in
Ruby and
[Music]
would cut off things with tiny tables
and do slowness and initial results okay
so essentially the software is out there
and anybody could test your results and
verify your results right and just have
it set up a cluster of whatever a
database will all the databases that
you've taken a look at so far and how
many databases did you take a look at by
now for the first round I think three in
the second three in the third so I guess
we're up to ten now maybe maybe 11 I've
almost lost track and there's been some
sort of side worth it was more
theoretical looking and modeling the
latest round I'm working on right now
it's probably gonna be another three
databases I'm hoping that will show up
Denson talks this spring so if you had
to categorize those results was it like
you know 90% just a pass with flying
colors everything was great and there
was just a very very few that broke or
was it all were bad or well what what
was the general kind of the type of
result that you get from those tests
it's always surprising I think every
time you go and measure something you
you discover something new and
fascinating about a system that you you
trusted and oftentimes you discover more
questions you never thought to ask this
is this is experimental isn't likee you
get to just throw random stuff at a
machine and unusual behaviors occur in
MongoDB for example I knew the defaults
weren't safe they just wrote to a socket
and did not check to see if it actually
went anywhere they just assumed you were
right was safe
like that's obviously wrong and you
could show that without too much trouble
but they were in the process of
migrating to a stronger one where you
would you would verify that at least one
machine is accepted it and I also knew
that that wasn't Satan was able to
demonstrate that what I didn't realize
was that there even the majority level
where it confirms act from the majority
of nodes in the cluster even that isn't
safe and I actually discovered this bug
and worked with the mago people to fix
it um where if and the network failed it
would check off the okay box and send
the request back to the client just to
get it out of its hair it's like all
right I don't know what to do with this
thing check okay you're done send it
back and so that that was sort of
unexpected and delightful behavior and
you know nothing was that surprising we
knew last right ones was bad the doctor
teaches the last ones is bad but it was
still the default because bachelor has a
bunch of customers who for various
historical reasons expected and one this
behavior and having an actual blog post
that could point to it says look you're
gonna drop seventy percent your data if
you use this thing in this way was sort
of okay so maybe we can maybe we can
spent just I don't know one one minute
at most with each of them just you know
just remember what you what you thought
of your results and what your general
impression was then we can go through
all of them so I have a list before me
and I will of course put the put the
list of the blog posts in the show notes
so let's start with with Postgres so the
best finding is it's a it's a subtle and
not perfectly scary phenomenon it just
leads to false negatives the reason is
that those because sort of does this two
phase commit thing where I'm going to
tell those guys okay can the transaction
post Christ goes and checks it's okay
commit and then sends back a response
saying okay you're done
and then we've both agreed that
transactions complete if that final
message is lost the TVC is not position
tolerance it will just stall forever and
so the client eventually does this
timeout and said okay your transaction
failed when in fact the transaction
couldn't succeed it okay I just managed
to show that experimentally you get into
situations where they say hey I did not
write the number two the number two
failed a transaction but in fact the
number two would appear in the final
read because post Christ had committed
it but the response had gotten lost
okay Redis Redis was a complete disaster
the sentiment protocol had numerous race
conditions and and all sorts of issues
was safety it would enter permanent
split-brain you would get independent
chunks of the cluster the default
separately and I think it never actually
recovered I think it just kept going
slip reign forever yeah unmitigated
disaster it's better now somewhat and in
fact anteriors is actually built his own
testing harness for doing perdition
tolerance tests so I'm really happy with
how that's progressed okay
so anti race for those who don't know is
the author is Salvatore San Filippo oval
Redis right okay so MongoDB you talked a
bit about it but maybe give us some more
detail about it yeah data at every
consistency level the unacknowledged
rights of course are not safe because
you're not checking to see if they
actually went anywhere you're just
throwing them out into the void and
hoping they arrive if you write to a
single node or to knows those are all
sound safe because if that node crashes
it may not have replicated its data to
the remaining nodes in the cluster and
so a new node a new leader can come up
with help knowledge of those rights and
then overwrite your original race you
have to write with write concern
majority and that also turned out to be
broken because it would claim things
accessible when they weren't that bug
was sense fixed I believe it took a tech
has published additional analysis at the
moment replication protocol I think
they're actually still bugs in it but I
haven't gone back and looked personally
one of my goals for this next round
objections to do a second attempt okay
react react lost staggering amounts of
data in last right wins mode this is not
a new result the docs tell you like it
isn't safe to do this you can only write
once in last right wins last right wins
essentially means any write wins when
precision occurs however if you use C or
D T's and and set addition as a safe
operation to do in a C or D T you
recover 100% of all rights and complete
availability so it does behave exactly
as you'd expect for an EP system you
just have to make sure use it once okay
so the next one is zookeeper that's a
different kind of system right now well
we always wouldn't have wouldn't have
categorized it as a as a as a database
but clearly in the datastore with a
particular purpose or typically used for
a particular purpose right yes for
configuration and state data it all has
to fit in RAM so it's not we even think
of as a sort of traditional little
teepee database but it has the advantage
that if you use sync commands it is
fully linearizable
and if you think you get linearizable
semi linearizable rights and possibly
stale reads so it's really a terrific
system for dealing like distributed
state machines okay that turned out to
pass with flying colors
the fact that I don't find a problem is
not evidence that no problems exist no
obvious problems exist yeah it's just
that it happened to pass that particular
set of tests and I a hammer on it for
quite a while wasn't able to find
another okay you would he be one I
haven't heard of before you know
attention because one of the founders
wrote some really questionable things
about the cap theorem and the
documentation it was extremely confused
the approach they took was essentially
to block forever and just accrue rights
until memory exploded obviously that
doesn't work particularly well it'll be
fine so long as you're right volume is
sufficiently low but you also stole all
your clients so it's you know it's
unlikely that your clients are willing
to tolerate 10 million sees or whatever
they're probably going to give up and
fail so it essentially becomes
unavailable completely during perdition
as opposed to having partial
availability Africa Kafka had a really
interesting bug I was reading the
replication design document before I
think about maybe oh wait I think it was
oh wait zero and they they had this new
sort of replication design where you had
a set of replicas that were kept in sync
with each other they proceeded in
lockstep but if a replica fell behind or
was not reachable it would be ejected
from the in sync replica set and this is
only go through zookeeper which is I
think a great choice for keeping your
cluster membership state the the tricky
bit is that they allowed the instinct
replica Jet Set to shrink below a
majority of nose so if you were careful
with your partitions it's possible to
get the instinct replica set down to a
single node which will still acknowledge
all of the rights that are performed so
the single node is busy saying like okay
yep I'm taking your data everything's
fine everything's fine but if that
single node then crashes or if it loses
at zookeeper connection the cluster will
have an election and choose one of the
other nodes which has no knowledge of
the rights that were acknowledged only
on that single node and that point
you've lost data that new node will take
over and over at the previous ones so to
find those kinds of scenarios did you
have to you know think of that once you
notice there's a single node happily
acknowledging that everything
find view did you change the tool to
actually look for that case and kill
that one note as well or how did you
find provoked those bugs so you make
them happen was the most tricky I I was
looking at the algorithm on the wiki and
kind of I had this like sense that it
wasn't right but I wasn't sure exactly
so I sketched out a bunch of things in a
whiteboard and I thought I found this
pattern that would lead to that problem
and so I actually had a chat with them I
think gee crepes actually that day and
it was like yeah you know that might be
plausible we're not sure we'll get back
to you we'll talk about it and so I went
and built the test and because it
requires that you shrinking sink replica
set first to a particular node you can't
just produce you stuff randomly anymore
it's not like a simple person would do
it you had to have this sort of one-two
punch of getting it down to a single
load or minority notes and then making
sure those lost connections so luckily
Jepsen has like a place you can hook in
an arbitrary failure scheduler and I was
able to write one that caused that
particular failure pattern and indeed it
did lose tons of data so I think I was
if I recall correctly that got changed
there's now a configuration swish which
you can flip the controls whether or not
elections possible now no mm-hmm okay so
the interesting thing that Kafka not not
even the cafe people claim in any way
that it's a database right but still you
can you can you can show the problem is
occurring in anything that stores data
and some kind that is distributed across
multiple nodes right anything will
exhibit those kinds of problems yeah
it's it's it's a long
oh it's maybe not what you think it was
a traditional database but it still was
a datastore preserve what about
Cassandra Cassandra had just introduced
a new transaction system comply with
transactions and I was able to show they
went deadlock hard which was a
delightful result anything when the
deadlock was fixed it also lost data so
that found two super bugs in their
transaction system plus a whole bunch of
interesting isolation problems and in
terminology issues and the docs
okay well I'll wrap it MQ now that's not
a database that I'll have to insist
yeah it's it's a queue much like Hakka
you know I still kind of think in those
databases they're just different shapes
there's a blog post which suggested
build
semaphore mutex on top of RabbitMQ and I
thought were like happy right and and of
course of all the data and we talked
about this back channel he's like yeah
this is obviously not right either
I wrote the thing will quietly change
that but it was still it was a little
good example of here's something some
people do you know trying to shape one
database into another how can we
demonstrate with them on state
properties whole truth okay and maybe
let's just pick let's go with the last
you as well so we have had city and
council seda council are both very
similar system zookeeper their
configuration stores and then for small
in memory data sets that are supposed to
be linearizable and both of them made
the same interesting choice so they're
made from the raft protocol which is as
so far analysis looks to be solid the
difficulty is that they're consistent
updates and existent reads oh yes is
consistent reads did not check to make
sure that the leader they were talking
to you was still the leader by the end
of the read operation and so a cluster
transition could occur and you could
wind up Rooney stale data I'm a final
one on the list is elastic search
elastic search was a complete disaster
he lost data from network positions that
were intersecting from network petitions
that were not intersecting from single
nodes being isolated even a single node
reboot could cause data loss it was it
was a spectacular failures sounds like
you had fun breaking down a number of
these companies using chips internally
to help it's worth of software and a lot
of them is sort of turned around they're
documenting these failure modes
monistic searching particular now has a
phenomenal Status page which talks about
all the sort of data loss issues and and
their priorities and links through all
the tickets I'm really happy with that
right so that if there's one thing
that's that I found utterly fascinating
it seems seems that you broke stuff and
then told people their systems are just
bad and completely broken and shouldn't
be built that way in the first place but
nobody really
he kept cursing of you that badly
everyone obviously people took a look at
the results and found them to be to be
valid and actually used it to their own
advantage is that is that a reasonable
assessment what happened or whether it
was there a lot of anger at you some
people are not and it has to do with
like how politely I approach the
database and how close implement angers
like again this is a social problem
humans are humans the results by and
large I think had been constructive and
and now it's also my goal to to help
users figure out what systems are safe
and how to analyze their own systems
also to help vendors improve their
safety but I'm one person you know
before I was doing this in my free time
on nights and weekends and these these
analyses take hundreds of hours per
database you know when you factor all
the the time right in the tooling and
and researching papers and writing out
the results it'll work so I can't I
can't be the key we departed for the
internet right like ultimately I had to
inspire the companies to care themselves
and then it becomes a competitive
advantage for them because they can
claim hey we're actually safe according
to these metrics so I think you
mentioned that before there are a lot of
papers as people can read they may not
be the most the most interesting my time
reading but there are there's a there is
a lot of research out there for that
stuff so TV listen people didn't do
their research properly before building
a distributed consistency resolution
protocol or or implementation keep in
mind that everybody who is building a
database isn't or tremendous pressure
financially interest time in terms of
staffing there's a ton of things that
have to happen and it's an incredibly
difficult job
so just because people didn't read
literature or unaware of it or didn't
design something correctly it's not that
they're bad engineers per se it's just
that these problems are sort of poorly
understood and there's not a culture to
support their understanding yet okay one
of the things I want to do with
Jefferson is change engineering culture
to be a little bit more aware of failure
modes and how to reason about them so it
depends on which which are the company
you talk to what their engineering
sure is like bachelor who places a very
high value on papers and it shows and
their engineering you know while I do
have data loss and corruption bugs from
time to time I think their their general
architecture has proven to be solid a
company like MongoDB you know they made
some obviously terrible choices as far
as safety goes but they also made those
choices because they knew they had to
get this database out store quickly to
build traction in the market so in some
cases is a deliberate trade-off you know
we're gonna do the less safe thing
people won't notice until later and by
that timing we can fix it okay which is
a valid business strategy I suppose I my
principle concerns that people document
and explain and communicate their their
uncertainty or their possible failure
most users I don't need people to be an
emergency I just want them to be honest
right so there's something life I'm very
interesting if I mean the different
trade-offs some sometimes they're even
valid trade-offs right as you mentioned
if it's if it's documented and if it's
if it's very openly communicated that
there are certain restrictions that you
have to be aware of you obviously have
to address them in your application
layer right you have to do something to
work with that database it might be okay
to lose some data maybe if you're using
it if you're using a search engine maybe
it doesn't matter that much if something
that you're right to it is lost
depending on what kind of stuff it is
that your search for or that you built
this in X for right so what other some
what are some of the strategies that you
can that you can use in your own
application or let me phrase it
differently what's a good strategy I
mean for developers if they look at all
those things are they supposed to pick
the one that Esther that they got the
best results in your in your testing
with Jepsen or what what are the kinds
of trade-offs that people have to make
and how to wait how do they address them
once they've made them with the data
store in their application layer you can
make two answers out of that if there
was too much of a question to ask
specific endorsements a because like not
every database is suitable for all all
problem classes right typically you're
going to choose several databases that
fit your particular needs as far as
availability performance and
distribution go and and also
you know just because I didn't find
problems doesn't mean there are problems
and you also have to consider other
factors like bergen omics availability
of tooling availability of expertise
gave hiring people to run the database
can you afford the licensing fees so
there's there's a lot of things you
balance in addition to safety just
because something is theoretically
unsafe does not mean you'll be bitten by
it um so you know I've been at several
companies now with elasticsearch and
prod and every one of them has been a
tiger fighter and you know that I would
not recommend elasticsearch at all if
you care about like having your database
cluster or having your search system
like actually available respond to
requests in it okay doesn't sound like
an endorsement it has a phenomenal API
it is probably the the the most popular
of the available tools there's plenty of
library support you know people continue
to choose it because search systems
don't actually have to have all your
data now I've seen it do something to do
things like lose a third to a 1/8 of the
data set from a new reboot and that
stage it starts to be really problematic
for us but in certain cases that's still
ok and if you're refilling it it's fine
ok so you know this is one of the things
where I want people to just think really
carefully about what kind of safety they
really need and then you choose the
database that will satisfy that level of
safety and in certain cases you can kind
of make a more loose cultural decision
like zookeeper at CD and console
zookeepers API is complicated the the
clients are not easy to understand it
has a really complicated connection
model and I mess it up all the time but
zookeeper uncomfortable city are
excellent tools for just you know for
the purpose of they're intended for I
would assume they are right for the
configuration in this case it's a
different way but even though NCD has I
think very nice simple HTTP API it has
been only been around for a couple of
years and so it has not yet hit all the
various interesting production and
failure modes that zookeeper has and
it's going to take time stabilized ok so
I think people are finding out with
console and SCD like oh there's Holly
surprising behaviour that the developers
haven't seen yet
because it's like oh this only happens
once you're at this request point this
cluster size that so believes you happen
hey then you get this weird explosion of
memory and then the GC pauses are over
and security knows also sees these
things so maturity is I think you know
even though you can be based on a solid
theoretical understanding it takes a
while or not so maybe let's talk a bit
about how you actually build Jepsen's
because one of the things that I found
interesting was the your choice of
closure for it was that just coincidence
because he happened to be familiar with
that language or was it a conscious
choice to use it for the purpose the
first proxy girl actually and it didn't
go very well I wound up using a ruby
deployment tool called salt acid that I
wrote to do the network automation like
killing nodes and causing network users
and then I wrote the analysis system in
closure because it has really nice
facilities for working with data and
because pretty much every database has a
JVM client somewhere so I'd accessed all
the regular Java clients they're decent
quality they're easy to interact with
and the performance and closure is
acceptable good so it was a natural
choice for those reasons okay so there
was no there was no particular strengths
the strength of closure that you could
exploit except for its general purpose
you know usefulness back-end language
and it's specially good with databases
because while it's certainly not as fast
as Java it's certainly a lot more
concise which makes it easier to sort of
reason about the correctness of your
code and to and to write complex data
analyses the hue lines the the newer
versions of Jepson actually are written
in closure for good reason they have
certain macros and ESL's and and so
forth that take much more advantage of
closures concurrency primitives of its
syntactic transformations those things
would be a little figurative quarter
different language I think okay do you
know of any comparable work are there
other tools like Jepson but other by
vendors or by other researchers it's
very much a system I built because I
needed it but our only address is a
great particular subproblem there are
quite a few academic network modeling
tools
but most of them are aimed at you you
write your algorithm inside their
language and it checks that the penny of
it spin and pommel are both algorithm
checking languages you can write
something in like C or a more formal
language like TL A+ and it will check
the model to make sure that it satisfies
their invariance you describe you can
you can run your entire network in a
simulated system that does actor message
passing stuff the the problem I have is
that of course I don't control anything
bases they're just you know programs
that run on Linux or whatever so I had
to have this black box system where I
could induce the failures externally and
insert the system externally and
hopefully get some useful results out of
it so Jeff's has a sort of funny shape
to account for that problem I'm not sure
so aunt iris summits were has his own
testing tool for Redis there are failure
tools for measuring Cassandra that are
internal react has extensive stuff for
an equipped check which is a generative
testing tool for Erlang and Haskell and
supports yeah I think most vendors have
heavy sorts of things actually
foundation DB is quite impressed me they
have a they have not only extensive
software simulation of the their message
passing system to verify safety but also
they have dedicated hardware that can
have induced failures they can actually
have a robot flip a switch on the switch
or whatever and turn it off and see what
happens
Wow okay so can you elaborate a bit on
how Jepson works internally yeah so
Jepsen has gone through a few iterations
I mentioned the sort of set addition and
problem earlier where you add numbers to
a set in a database and read it back but
I've wanted to test more strong Cinci
classes like linearize ability and for
that i can't just do unordered
operations like set i need to have more
complex data types like a lock or
integer with compare and set operations
or maybe an an SQL table i'd like to be
able to model these complicated things
and verify their correctness so I've
written a tool called Knossos which does
model checking against a history will it
up evaluate with our model like a
register or a set
or QED whether that model is consistent
with the operations we observed from a
database and then Jepsen is responsible
for building a bunch of random
operations like set the registers
numbers to if and only if it's currently
three or at the number three to the Q DQ
something and then it has clients which
will apply those operations the system
so the combination of the the randomly
generated operations the history of how
those operations played out in the
system whether different clients
actually saw that to do is do and then
the model checker verifying that that
history is consistent with what we think
the system should do those three give
you a measure of safety it reminds me a
bit of the of the approach taken by by
things like quick check it's the same
exact thing okay yeah it's real check
where you have a model that describes
what the system should do in simple
concrete terms okay if I if I add a
number to register the new number should
be the new value the register should be
that number plus the old value or if I
am done with the set it should be one
bigger and if I do it read I should see
that number you you write down simple
laws about the system and then generate
a bunch of random instructions execute
them as you have um I go back to some
theory if that's okay with you there has
been a whole lot of research into
algorithms for for resolving this this
fork for finding a strategy to result
the consistency problems that arise
other some some basic ones that people
should know that you would like to point
people to the gold standard is paxos you
know it if you don't know what you need
choose linear instability you know it's
going to be the safest of all you can't
kind of explain what what Paxos does how
does the algorithm work explainable in a
podcast you know honestly taxes is a is
a subtle and dark magic which I'm not
qualified to explain verbally I need a
white board
I can't even then it's a little dodgy
for me the the end result is it Paxos
gives you a system of participating
nodes in a cluster which can come to
agreements on certain decisions in
practice you can even train
that consensus algorithm into other
things like a replicated state machine
or a log there's another protocol which
is much simpler called raft which is as
far as we know an equivalent paxos and
there's also Zab which is the zookeeper
atomic broadcast paper and the Zab has
actually implemented inside of zoo
keeper which are slightly different
things all of those also offer linearize
ability so as a lowly lowly application
developer I don't actually have to
implement them because I hopefully I
have some have used some tool that has
implemented those things correctly do I
have to know how they work do I do I
have to know the consequences of using
them because I mean I have to have some
you know some insight into what it is
that I'm that I'm using there right I
work all you need to know is what
classes of history do they allow and in
a linearizable system you're guaranteed
ones your operation completes it's going
to be visible your every operation will
appear to take place between the time
you send the message starting it and
when you get back the result saying hey
it's done and now there are other
algorithms if you have sequential
consistency you no longer get that
real-time guarantee your message could
come back saying hey it's done but it
can logically take effect later or in
the case of read committed you can get
certain read anomalies for okay I
recommit a data but a might impossible
for me to still see a phantom for a
predicate not to be consistent with the
current state when acronym you mentioned
a number of times was CR DT can you give
us a brief introduction into into that
concept what does it stand for and and
what does it what does it mean so CR DT
is a convergent replicated data type we
all use data types right like assess or
strings or arrays a replicated data type
is one that can exist in multiple places
so you can have a copy on one computer
in the copy or another and if it's
convergent we want to guarantee that if
those copies communicate they will come
together and to some final value that we
can agree on so this is really useful
for AP systems where you might update a
counter on two different nodes that
don't communicate with each other and
then
later they exchange information and come
to a new counter value which should
include both counter increments so
taking that example how would that be
implemented what if they do use some
version cracking or timestamps or is is
that the the internal implementation of
that particular CR DT then the really
nice thing about C or D T's is that if
you implement them if you follow these
simple rules you basically get safe
convergence for free everything else
becomes a performance optimization so
the rules you have to do to be assured
et are to be associative community of an
idempotent associativity means that is
you able to change the parentheses
around the function application F of a
and B and then applying that to F of F
and C that should be equivalent to
switching the nesting order 370 means
that it's argument order independent so
F of a and B is equal to F of e a so
those two things mean that I can apply
the operations any order on any replicas
at the same results okay the last one
idempotence means that if I apply the
same operation multiple times
it only takes effect once and that's
critical because it means I don't have
to only send a message to my peers once
I think keep sending them my update over
and over and over again and it will have
the same safety properties so the
conversion strategy for C or D T once
you follow those rules for your merge
function is you just few companies of
yourself at everybody else and they spew
copies back at you and you just call the
merge function to combine them and
you're guaranteed to come up with the
same answer so other than standard
implementations of C or D T's of various
kinds in standard libraries that people
can use or is that just something for
database vendors to to make use of I
think does it so there's your keys
built-in to react and there's something
kind of like C or D T's in Cassandra I
think some of the secure data types are
in some heart things like sets in I
think Redis cluster might end up looking
somewhat lycée or deities at some point
and you can certainly employment on the
database so in react all data types
should be C or D T's and once we're
using strong consistency buckets make
Cassandra
all of your motives should be sir duties
and you can implement that logic just by
having your own merge function in your
your code so you read a value merge in
the right back okay now there are some
common ones
the INRIA papers is describing CEO
duties and also what's the what's the
second paper anyway if you if you google
for sneaking papers crisp nickel John
has a bunch of these and they describe a
few common implementations you can build
last right wins registers you can build
sets that grow only sets you can add to
and then remove from once sets where you
can observe anything you've already
removed you can build lists so you have
an ordering relation you can get maps of
certain certain types of maps it it's a
little bit tricky because in remember
for them to be converging you have to
give up with certain properties about
visibilities so your counters for
example maybe all of your inserts to a
counter are going to be safe and match
the scene but you don't know when
they'll be seen and maybe the space
guarantees are different so in a counter
you have to have a slot for each and
every actor in the system for a vertical
we're only counting for an observer
moves that you have to carry with you a
tag that identifies all the answers and
all the solutions so these space
complexity requirements are typically
worse than a linearizable systems would
be so we've covered on the ground talked
a lot about theory and we've talked
about a lot of actual systems so maybe
first of all is it a reasonable approach
for a software engineer to just pick one
solution and stick with it or maybe two
if they have different needs and and can
they use your post as a as a guideline
is to assess the qualities of the
systems I think the post will be useful
in figuring out how to think about a
system I don't think you can use them as
like oh by this database you ultimately
I try to stress this in each post and
every talk it's up to you to measure
your systems correctness and to figure
out if the invariants you need are
provided by the database so I you can
you can read Jepson posts to figure out
okay can I get this isn't linearizable
but those may be out of date right I
can't keep updating things all the time
and you might discover that there are
certain requirements that I just haven't
talked about which switching age from
your database so ultimately I want to
give people the tooling in Jepsen and
and push the vendors to provide tooling
as well so that you can evaluate these
for yourself I think in in more general
terms as a software engineer you're
going to need to combine multiple data
stores so you might have maybe Kafka is
a log store and cassandra for immutable
AP storage and Ivy react for for a
snooty store and maybe zookeeper for a
linearizable store and you might be
shuffling operations into and out of
these different data stores maybe they
post Kratz maybe this is a shortened
Postgres in there for her strong
serializable operation is over subsets
of the data set I think you'll find that
your your use cases once you start
getting up to scale require that you use
different data types and different data
stores for different data volumes I
think the degree you'll have really high
volume stuff that can't fit and
zookeeper Postgres and so you have to
start charting it yourself or you have
to start using an ApS or like Cassandra
for your high throughput just ok so what
are some good resources some some places
people puts people could start if they
want to familiarize themselves with this
topic more I think seem like cm yeah ok
he's got a great reading list for
distributed systems engineers and that's
that's where I would go for a theory
I've written a blog post on strong
consistency models and Peter Bayless has
written much better formal work on the
topic its consistency so those those are
good resources if you're interested in
more Theory if you're interested in a
short overview of Jepson
I think the ACM queue article on network
relation of frequency might be if you
use because it tells you sort of here's
a bunch of different feeling or modes
that we saw in production systems
it's an overview of the different post
mortems that we've seen and about
networked petition failures and the
Jeff's impose themselves kind of show
you exemplars of here's how a system can
fail but I think it's
look at those those case reports and not
as sort of generalize the results okay
so thank you very much for this for
parolees information my head will
explode into there in very few seconds
so thanks a lot for your time and happy
to have had you in the film thank you
for software engineering radio this has
been Stefan tilaka thank you for
listening thanks for listening to se
radio an educational program brought to
you by I Triple E software magazine for
more information about the podcast
including other episodes visit our
website @ SC - radioman to provide
feedback you can write comments on each
episode on the website or write a review
on itunes mention a message us on
twitter at se radio or search for the
software engineering radio group on
LinkedIn Google+ or Facebook you can
also email us at team @ SC - radio net
this and all other episodes of SU radio
is licensed under the creative commons
two-point-five license thanks again for
your support
[Music]
you